Mss.Rec.20 Mss.Rec.20
American Philosophical Society
Songs and Dances of the Rural Ottawa and Chippewa Indians
1953-1955
Mss.Rec.20
American Philosophical Society
6.0 Reel(s)
Albert, Whitney
Chevis, Roy
Kenosha, David
Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
Pamp, Betty
Pamp, Jack
Pamp, Joan
Peters, Jim
Rickard, Glenna
Shagonaby, Susan
Shalifoe, Thomas
Soney, William
Sprague, Selkirk
Thomas, Eli
Thompson, Stith, 1885-1976
Walpole Island Choir.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gertrude Kurath. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Catholic Church--Hymns; Indians of North America--Michigan--Folklore; Indians of North America--Michigan--History; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Indians of North America--Michigan--Religion; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882--Criticism and interpretation; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882. Song of Hiawatha; Methodist Church; Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa Indians--Religion; Revivals--Michigan; Sound recordings
- Native Songs
  - Woodpecker Song, 1954; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:53; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Cross Village (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Walking on Grass, 1954; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:30; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Eagle Dance, 1954; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:39; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Cross Village (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Bear Dance, 1954; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Maple Sugar Translation, 1954; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Drinking Song, 1954; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:16; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Cross Village (Mich.); Drinking songs; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Hoot Owl 1, 1954; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:06; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - War Rally, 1954; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa language
  - Hoot Owl 2, 1954; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Scalp Song, 1954; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:28; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Deer Song, 1954; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Baraga County (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Social Dance, 1954; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:23; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Baraga County (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Partner Song, 1954; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:21; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
  - Canoe Song, 1954-07-02; 01-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:17; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Mikado (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Medicine Song, 1954-07-02; 01-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:59; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Brave Song, 1954; 01-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:40; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Tracking Song, 1954; 01-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:50; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - White Pigeon, 1954; 01-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:54; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Scope and Contents note
    Recording contains some silent gaps and tape distortion.
  - Trapper, 1954; 01-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:06; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Coon Song, 1954-07-02; 01-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:51; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Rabbit Song, 1954-07-02; 01-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:00; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Cousin Song, 1954; 01-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:34; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Hoot Owl, 1954-07-02; 01-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:57; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Hunter's Song, 1954; 01-24; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:50; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Red Blanket, 1954; 01-25; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:51; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Drinking Song, 1954; 01-26; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Drinking songs; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Mikado (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Pipe Dance, 1954; 01-27; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Mikado (Mich.); Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - War Dance, 1954; 01-28; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:20; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Albert
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Michigan; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - War Dance, 1954; 01-29; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Corn Dance, 1954; 01-30; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:06; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Drinking Song, 1954; 01-31; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:31; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Albert
    Drinking songs; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Michigan; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Longfellow's Use of Michigan Indian Tales, 1955-03-26; 01-32; 1.0 .mp3; 00:42:47; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thompson, Stith, 1885-1976
    Recording of a talk given at a symposium titled "Michigan Indian Lore since 'Hiawatha'," held by the Michigan Folklore Society, of which Gertrude P. Kurath was Chairman.
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Folklore; Indians of North America--Michigan--History; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882--Criticism and interpretation; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882. Song of Hiawatha; Michigan
- Catholic Hymns
  - New Year Hymn, 1954; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:41; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From tape titled "Catholic Hymns."
    Catholic Church--Hymns; Cross Village (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Indians of North America--Michigan--Religion; Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa Indians--Religion
  - Kakina Minawasida, 1954; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:42; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
  - Gagangoiian, 1954; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:58; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
  - Kitchitwa Marie, 1954; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
  - Adeste Fideles, 1954; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:42; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
  - Gwanatch Marie, 1954; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:39; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Kitchitwa Marie, 1954; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:42; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Includes English conversation discussing the meaning of the lyrics. From tape titled "Catholic Hymns."
  - Sagitoda Jesus Wiiaw, 1954; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:24; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Mojag Anamiewin, 1954; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:30; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Catholic Church--Hymns; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Indians of North America--Michigan--Religion; Mikado (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa Indians--Religion
  - Gwanatch Beatrice, 1954; 02-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:15; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Jesus Wegwisiian, 1954; 02-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:34; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Baraga County (Mich.); Catholic Church--Hymns; Indians of North America--Michigan--Religion; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion
- Camp Meeting
  - Revival Song, O Bägish 1, 1953-09-06; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:18; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Hymn sung in Chippewa with some English responses from congregation. Recorded at Chippewa Free Methodist Camp Meeting Revival Service. English title of hymn: "O for a thousand tongues"
    Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa Indians--Social life and customs; Revivals--Michigan
  - More, more about Jesus, 1953-09-06; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:39; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Recorded at Chippewa Free Methodist Camp Meeting Revival Service
  - O bägish 2, 1953-09-06; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Recorded at Chippewa Free Methodist Camp Meeting Revival Service. English title of hymn, "O for a thousand tongues," played to tune of "I would not be denied."
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - There's a Crown, 1953-09-06; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Sermon and Jesus Ishpeming hymn, 1953-09-06; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:35; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Peters, Jim
    Sermon followed by collection during hymn. Recorded at Chippewa Free Methodist Camp Meeting Revival Service. English title of hymn: "Jesus, my all"
    Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church--Sermons; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa Indians--Social life and customs; Revivals--Michigan
  - Prayer, 1953-09-06; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Sprague, Selkirk
    Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa Indians--Social life and customs; Prayers
  - Doxology and Benediction, 1953-09-06; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:13; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Soney, William
    Only second half of doxology recorded. Recorded at Chippewa Free Methodist Camp Meeting Revival Service.
    Benedictions; Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa Indians--Social life and customs
- Methodist Hymns
  - Jesus Ishpeming 2, 1954; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:44; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Sung by congregation. English title of hymn: "Jesus, my all."
  - O bägish 3, 1954; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:19; Chamberlain, Mrs.; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Soney, Fred
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Sung by congregation. English title of hymn: "O for a thousand tongues."
  - When I can read, 1954; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:00; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Sung by Walpole Island choir.
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language; Walpole Island (Lambton, Ont.)
  - O bägish 4, 1954; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:37; Chamberlain, Mrs.; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Sung by "Chamberlain and Congregation." English title of hymn: "O for a thousand tongues."
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Kenawagash, 1954; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:34; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Sung by "Chamberlain and Congregation."
  - Jesus Ishpeming 3, 1953-08-16; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." English title of hymn: "Jesus, my all."
    Hastings (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Jesus Ishpeming 4, 1954-07-02; 04-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Mount Pleasant (Mich.); Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Jesus Ishpeming 5, 1953-11-04; 04-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:52; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Ann Arbor (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Onda shansa, version 1, 1953-08-16; 04-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:12; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." English title of hymn, "Come, thou fount of every blessing"
  - Onda shansa, version 2, 1953; 04-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:49; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
  - Onda shansa, version 3, 1954-04-30; 04-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:41; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Pamp, Betty; Pamp, Joan; Rickard, Glenna; Thomas, Eli
  - Seneca hymn (tune Jesus [Ishpeming] 2), 1954; 04-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:47; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lyons, Mrs.
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns."
    Calhoun County (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Methodist Church--Hymns; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - O bägish 5, 1954-09-14; 04-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Pamp, Betty; Pamp, Joan; Rickard, Glenna
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." English title of hymn, "O for a thousand tongues"
  - Seneca ([O bägish 5] tune), 1954-09-14; 04-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:28; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lyons, Mrs.
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." English title of hymn: "O for a thousand tongues."
  - Chi Anoki, 1954-07-02; 04-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:32; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Pamp, Betty; Pamp, Joan; Rickard, Glenna; Thomas, Eli
    From tape titled "Methodist Hymns." Recording is cut-off before completion of song.
- Text of Methodist Hymns
  - Texts of Methodist Hymns - Translations by Eli Thomas, 1954; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:31; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Methodist Church--Hymns; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion
- Miscellany
  - Story of Deer, 1954; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:03; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    First told in Ottawa, then English.
    Deer--Folklore; Michigan; Ottawa Indians--Folklore
  - Benediction, 1954; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:42; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Soney, William
    In Chippewa.
    Benedictions; Methodist Church; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Benediction, 1954; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:22; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
  - Terms: sacrifice, cross, 1953; 06-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:13; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Chippewa Christian terminology. Silence gap in program from 2:13 to 2:27.
    Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Ojibwa language
  - Story of Hunter, 1953; 06-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:45; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Chippewa story in English.
    Hunters--Folklore; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Folklore
  - Turkey-in-the-straw (fiddle), 1953; 06-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Instrumental only.
    Fiddling; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - 'Neath the Old Olive Tree (Guitars and song at Camp Meeting), 1953-09-06; 06-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:09; Chevis, Roy; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Guitar--Performance; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Methodist Church; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion